welcome to meditating with john vervicky
we live stream this every weekday
morning at 9 30 a.m eastern time with
monday's alternating between a new
lesson of dharma day
and a review of the whole ecology of
practices called upaya day
if you're joining us for the first time
you're most welcome for previous lessons
and sit see the description
i recommend you then go and do lesson
one immediately
continue meeting with us do a new lesson
or two
every week and soon you will be caught
up and integrated with us
i would ask everybody to please like the
stream on in order to increase its
visibility on the youtube algorithm so i
can help as many people as possible
at the end of every sit there is a q a
uh please limit questions to this entire
course ecology of practice that we're
doing
however if you have more general
questions uh please come
to my general q a every third friday of
the month
live streamed on youtube at 3 p.m
eastern time
all right i'd like to also uh remind
people that we're going to be starting
um
the western wisdom tradition um
we've done a lot from the eastern and we
won't
set that behind we will continue to
practice but we're also going to start
moving into the western a reminder that
the book you
will need uh very soon and like like i'm
going to start talking about it on
monday
is the wisdom of hypatia uh by
mcclellan also another cognitive
scientist strongly recommended
that and this is the order in which you
should try and get them uh
that uh in order to get this very
as soon as possible too uh pierre goes
what is ancient philosophy
it is a good supplementary reading and
background uh this is basically
uh the argument that ancient philosophy
is a wisdom tradition
it is a way of life it is a spiritual
exercise as
pierre pierredo uh famously argued
uh a little bit more down the road
especially when we move towards the end
of the whole trajectory which is the
neoplatonic trajectory
i strongly recommend getting this
beautiful little gem by arthur versus
lewis
arthur versus lewis uh the perennial
philosophy
this is not aldous huxley's idea this is
a different
uh proposal uh one that is more
plausible than huxley's
uh which is that neoplatonism actually
forms
uh sort of the spiritual grammar of
western
uh spirituality and mysticism so and
that
and western includes uh christianity
judaism
and islam so strongly recommend the
wisdom of hypatia
by mcclellan uh you need that that's
pretty much going to be mandatory for us
going forward uh
strongly recommended you get as soon as
possible as well what is ancient
philosophy by pirado
and then a little bit later down the
road uh the uh perennial philosophy
by arthur versus lewis
all right now the next uh thing is
i was sent a wonderful
print by nicholas and i just want to
share that with everyone
and i want to thank nicholas for this
wonderful print
he also sent a wonderful
card with prince on them both to jason
and tomorrow
uh thanking them and so we together all
three of us
uh want to thank nicholas for the kind
gifts they're very encouraging
thank you very much okay
a reminder that we didn't i wasn't able
to get through
everything jason and i were pinch
hitting
on monday we didn't quite get through
the entire ecology and so
uh after we do the sit i'll also go
through alexia divina for us
okay i think that's everything uh wow
you can tell this is a real thing hey we
have lots of announcements in business
anyways uh let's set your phones to do
not disturb we'll get ready
uh we will as always
begin by chanting and then we'll go into
the silent set
we'll come out of the set of course uh
we're doing the promises
dulexia and then hopefully uh we'll have
some
we will because uh we're not on a heart
out today
and we'll address some questions that
have been held over all right everyone
so uh we will begin when i say begin
begins
one
oh
[Music]
one
oh
[Music]
um
one
[Music]
um
begin your silence set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your beginning consciousness
cognition character and communicates
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay let us now please move to lectio
divina
set the intention
reverence for the revelation trusting in
transformation
this is from wilka buddha in glory
seems appropriate given the wonderful
print by nicholas
center of all centers core of course
almond self-enclosed and growing sweet
all this universe to the farthest stars
and beyond them
is your flesh your fruit
now you feel how nothing clings to you
your vast
shell reaches into endless space and
there the thick
rich fluids rise and flow illuminated in
your infinite peace
a billion stars go spinning through the
night blazing high above your head
but in you is the presence that will be
when all the stars are dead
so this is very rich for me uh the image
of course of the buddha
and many of the phrases are are are
are resonating with me but the ending
seems to
be really present for me today but in
you
is the presence that will be when all
the stars are dead
so first of all what comes up for me is
just
that sense of presence what it is when
you're with
somebody for example that sense of
presence when they're really present
you feel really present in a situation
now that can be intensified
in the flow state and how it can be even
more intensified
in meditation and then how that presence
right the presence is
look is it's astounding it's like the
presence itself is continuous with
it participates in
that the presence of being itself the
way
out of eternity everything is being
presenced in time out of
all of the indeterminate possibilities
there's determinate
actualities that that
is calling me to is that don't think
that the buddha didn't think it
buddha is it not egotistically
identification
but non-egoic identification the buddha
is that it's given me a sense of what it
is
to cultivate my inner sage my buddha
nature to come into that sense
of a presence that deepens me into the
depths of things
it calls to me
you can feel it right now is a calling
to me a very
powerful calling
my inner sage just plugged into
something
prose is from john scottis regina
one of the greatest of the neoplatonic
christians i regard him as the
culmination
of the entire history of dialectic
socratic neoplatonic dialectic
we ought not to understand god and
creation
as two things distinct from each other
but as one
and the same for both the creature
by subsisting is in god oh think about
how this resonates with the wilka
and god by manifesting himself in a
marvelous
and ineffable manner creates himself in
the creature
the invisible making himself visible yes
do you see that that that's the presence
that we were just talking about
and the incomprehensible comprehensible
and the hidden revealed
and the unknown known and what is
without form and species formed and
specific
and the super essential essential of the
supernatural natural
and the simple composite and the
accident-free subject to accident
and the infinite finite and the
unsubscribed subscribed
and the super temporal temporal and the
creator of all things created
in all things and the maker of all
things
made in all things and the eternal
begins to be and immobile he moves into
all things
and becomes all things in all things
this
is just so resonating with the rilka
the and the the line that's coming out
for me is the
invisible becoming visible that whole
process of
the ineffable coming into what's
intelligible
that that profound deepest present
presence
goddess is telling me that god is both
like is both it is is that movement
it's like god is the moreness into the
suchness of everything god is the soul
of being
what does that mean for me what would it
be for me to live that way
seeing and being that way remembering
sati that
in every moment how would that
challenge my notions of god how would
that challenge my notions
of sacredness how would that challenge
my notions of being
and myself
so let's address some of the questions
may yank romani name of the books again
yes i'll hold them up as well the wisdom
of
hypatia by mcclellan
what is ancient philosophy
by pierre haddow
[Music]
perennial philosophy by arthur versus
the books that i'm using for lectio are
the enlightened heart that's the poetry
by stephen mitchell
and the enlightened mind for the pros
that's all the books i was using today
so i hope that answered your question
remember uh and some of you are doing
this that in addition to questions
comments and observations are welcomed
seriously welcomed dimitar i noticed
that the first ever distraction that
comes
up once i reach the decent level of
focus and interest is the very fact that
i'm meditating
it's almost like there's some underlying
anxiety that's making me turn my
attention towards
checking whether i'm meditating and
consequently i find it difficult
to renew my interest in my breath uh any
advice
yes um so the is the very fact that
you're meditating and then
you you come into question um
whether or not you're actually
meditating
so um sorry i don't mean to sound this
uh
this is not meant to be flippant then
stop
meditating in a sense of that there's
this specific thing you have to be do
uh doing to be doing meditation um
and uh give me a moment because that
sounds offhanded i don't mean by that
um just keep doing what you're doing
and when that thing comes up just label
it
as checking and do not begin the
investigation
because when you are beginning the
you are not just labeling and stepping
back from it you are getting involved
with the content of
checking oh checking it's just a
distraction
maybe i'm meditating maybe i'm not but
i'm just gonna start
following the breath again
this is a moment you think about you
know
the frog for me represents you know the
trust in the transformation
this is a moment ultimately of
entrusting yourself
to the buddha the dharma and the sangha
there's nothing that anybody can say to
you not me
not god himself that would
have the capacity to remove that
well of doubt because as soon as you
open to it and you all of you know that
i
take doubt as a cognitive process
seriously that's what i
that's not what i'm talking about here
i'm talking about the doubt
that will never be satisfied no matter
what evidence it is given
that's the so it's an anxious doubt as
dimitar
correctly points out
you have to trust that even if you're
not doing it perfectly correctly
perfectly right in the end it doesn't
matter
as long as you maintain the continuity
of practice i know that sounds like but
and there's the
voice in your hands but no but there is
nothing
beyond that
if your life transforms
that is your feedback that is your
feedback there is
nothing within your introspective
awareness
that will give a infinite certainty
to quell that infinite kind of debt
i understand deeply believe me that
that this is not an easy thing
but doing the checking after you get on
meditating
is to actually get involved with the
content rather than the labeling
you have to try returning in trust
without checking am i doing it correctly
to the practice you have to trust
in the practice and the process it's not
a blind trust
because there's the buddha the dharma
the sangha
and how that unfolds in your life as i
mentioned many times
but that that part of your left
hemisphere that likes to take credit for
everything
and undermine anything that it doesn't
instantiate
that it's not running it's a useful
thing by the way that's why we have it
it's adaptive
but like everything else like every
other adaptive process
it can become a source it can be
hijacked it can become a source
of self-deception self-destructive
behavior
i'm speaking from a long-term experience
with this kind of
hyper vigilance this is why right effort
right concentration right meditation
are so strongly emphasized by the buddha
he doesn't mean right in the sense
of meeting some standard of perfection
he means right like a dextrous grip
a flowing grip that is adjusting and
adapting
and continually self-correcting because
it is not
achieving some state of final perfection
i hope that's helpful to you dimitar i
really deeply empathize
uh with what you're what you're
wrestling with um
and so i hope that you can
at least get a glimmering taste of what
i'm talking about
and keep centering your attention on
that until it grows of its own accord
matthew mccready good to see you again
matthew
i know that alongside the internal chi
kung practices their external practices
more in line with physical development
what role should the development of the
body have in the ecology of practices
the the the development of the body and
the development of the mind are not
separate developments um this is why i
always say there's no friend
more important than your own mind and
body uh there's a deep
continuity between mind and body
so there i mean in this this goes even
into basic stuff like i was talking
about when we're doing the walking
practice
embodied balance
the balance that you're training when
you're moving
and that the embodied balance and
coordination in the movement
the cerebellum of course is being
activated for that
but that same activation comes into
place when we are trying to get
balance and coordination in our lives
the cerebellum is at work there there's
a deep continuity
developing in the body and the
developing of the mind
are two sides of the same coin
this is why uh i throughout i've tried
to
and i it's hard to tell to what degree
this is
actually part of the asiatic
experience of buddhism and taoism or the
degree to which
it's a western misappropriation but the
way
mindfulness has become a very
disembodied practice
um in the west for a lot of people this
is something i've tried to
compensate because i was taught
something very different and that is
very consonant
with our best cognitive science so
developing the body which isn't the same
thing as
you know doing just fitness practices
you want to do things
that train the body in ways that are
resonant
with right deeply continuous invoking
the same basic
fundamental principles as training the
mind and vice versa
mark mark
welcome mark it's always great to have
you here observation
chanting has all kinds of interesting
side effects over time for me
to today i've seen up to unlock some
inflammation of tension somehow
deep in my body instantly calming for my
whole self
well thank you mark um i don't know if
that was for today or from a previous
day but the
observation is very helpful because
chanting is exactly we we
we are trying to invoke we're trying not
we're not just representing
we're not just it's not just happening
we are invoking
the deep continuity between the mind and
body that the mind befriends the body
and trains the body and then the body
befriends and trains the mind and
enchanting
we are invoking that we are accentuating
it and we are
celebrating it
so thank you all very much for joining
for today this was a wonderful
sangha it always is um
it's it's it's it's like uh
it every time it's like a different song
i want to of course thank uh my dear
friend and technomagemar
and uh my beloved son jason who is
beside behind the scenes with them are
uh doing a lot doing a lot of pinching
he did a lot on monday
i want to again thank nicholas for the
wonderful gifts
he gave to all of us uh and jason and
amara also want to thank you
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video you will also
find links to the lecture series
awakened from meaning crisis the
dialogue series
voices with raviki where these themes
are
put into relationship to other themes
and situated with a more encompassing
uh framework of as pierre hadil would
say philosophy as a way of life
please invite others who might benefit
from this series
please i hope you guys met last tues
yesterday
on tuesday on uh the discord server
please join the discord server
to chat with others to practice with
others uh to
help develop the buddha the dharma and
the sangha the link is in the
description
uh brett and mark are no doubt here in
the sangha
to help guide you reminder that we do
this every weekday morning at 9
30 eastern time
remember continuity of practice remember
what i said to dimitar
and i'm saying it to myself to remember
it too continuity of practice is more
important than sheer quantity
of practice and there is no enemy worse
than your own mind and body
but there's no friend no ally no true
companion on the path
as great as your own mind and body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other
take good care everyone i'll see you
tomorrow
you